Guide to the Fellowship of Christian Athletes, Duke University Chapter Records, 1960 - 1965
Duke University. University Archives
Fellowship of Christian Athletes, Duke University Chapter records 1960 - 1965
Fellowship of Christian Athletes. Duke University chapter.
0.75 linear feet Extent: 750 Items
Duke University. University Archives
The Fellowship of Christian Athletes is a social and religious group for athletes and coaches. The Duke University chapter was founded in 1960. Records include correspondence, reports, history, financial materials, meeting notices, posters, programs, conference materials, membership lists, publications, clippings, and press releases. Major subjects include Duke University students, college sports, sports camps, religious life at Duke University, male college students, Christianity, leadership, and fellowship. Materials range in date from 1960 to 1965. English.
uafoca
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Fellowship of Christian Athletes, Duke University Chapter Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1975.
Historical Note
The Fellowship of Christian Athletes, a national organization, was founded in 1954 by Don McClanen. The Fellowship of Christian Athletes challenges coaches and athletes at the professional, college, high school, junior high, and youth levels to use the medium of athletics to learn leadership and moral values of the Christian faith. In 1956, coaches and 256 athletes attended the first national sports camp at Estes Park, Colorado. By 1964, summer programs were also established at Lake Geneva, Wisconsin and Black Mountain, North Carolina. By 1989, there were 40,000 official members. Close to 14,000 people attended summer camps in 1995. Campus programs called Huddles were established in 1966 to provide a peer-group meeting structure for camp attendees during the school year. The number of campuses with Huddle fellowships grew to around 6,600 by 1997. The organization is headquartered in Kansas City, Missouri.
The Duke University chapter of Fellowship of Christian Athletes was installed in 1960. Like other chapters, the Duke University chapter emphasizes leadership and fellowship among athletes and their communities. The Duke University chapter included baseball, basketball, football, and track players and coaches, but football players were the chapter's most well-represented group during the early 1960s. Informal chapter meetings were held weekly and monthly. Weekly meetings were for students only, while monthly meetings included a guest speaker during dinner. Members of the Duke chapter attended summer conferences, presented programs to churches, schools, and clubs, and assisted other colleges with forming chapters.
Religious groups at Duke University, alumni, and people in the community supported the chapter financially. Annual sermons were held in the Duke University Chapel to raise awareness of the chapter's activities. During the spring, the Athletics Department sponsored a Blue-White Spring Football Scrimmage to help the chapter raise funds for conference tuition. The Fellowship of Christian Athletes program at Duke University was managed in cooperation with the Durham County High Schools, which provided means for recruiting new athletes to play at Duke University.
As of 2003, the Fellowship of Christian Athletes is active at Duke University.
Collection Overview
Contains materials pertaining to Fellowship of Christian Athletes, a social and religious group for Christian athletes and coaches at Duke University. Records include correspondence, reports, history, financial materials, meeting notices, posters, programs, conference materials, membership lists, publications, clippings, and press releases. Major subjects include Duke University students, college sports, sports camps, religious life at Duke University, male college students, Christianity, leadership, and fellowship. Materials range in date from 1960-1965.
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be accessed under the following subject headings in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
Christian leadership; Christianity -- Study and teaching; College sports -- United States -- Religious aspects -- Christianity.; Duke University. Dept. of Athletics; Duke University -- Sports; Duke University -- Students; Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc; Fellowship of Christian Athletes; Male college students -- United States -- North Carolina -- Durham; Recreation leadership; Religious activities; Sports camps.; Sports -- Religious aspects -- Christianity -- History.; Sports -- United States -- Religious aspects -- Christianity.; Students -- Religion; Clippings
Contents of Collection
- Container List:
  - Correspondence, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual reports, 1962-1965 (Folder 2)
  - Chartering a chapter and local history, undated (Folder 3)
  - Community support and contributors, 1960-1965 (Folder 4)
  - Financial materials, 1960-1965 (Folder 5)
  - Fundraising, 1960-1965 (Folder 6)
  - Meeting notices and posters, ca. 1960-1962 (Folder 7)
  - Blue - White Football Game, ca. 1962 (Folder 8)
  - Duke Chapel benefit services, 1960-1963 (Folder 9)
  - Conferences, 1961-1965 (Folder 10)
  - Conference, Lake Geneva, Wis., 1960-1962 (Folder 11)
  - Conference, Henderson Harbor, N.Y., 1963-1965 (Folder 12)
  - National Conference Committee materials, 1961-1965 (Folder 13)
  - City-wide rallies, ca. 1961-1965 (Folder 14)
  - Membership lists, undated (Folder 15)
  - The Christian Athlete, 1960-1963 (Folder 16)
  - General Fellowship of Christian Athletes literature, ca. 1960-1965 (Folder 17)
  - Clippings and press releases, 1960-1965 (Folder 18)
Related Material
Intervarsity Christian Fellowship records.
University Archives, Duke University.